Guide to the World War II Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- CIVILIAN CORRESPONDENCE, DIARIES AND MEMORABILIA, Series III
  - Finland, 1939 (Box 44, Folder 6)
  - France, 1939-1946 (Box 44, Folder 7-11)
  - France - Debost correspondence, 1940-1945 (Box 44, Folder 12)
  - Germany, 1939-1941 (Box 44, Folder 13-14)
  - Germany - Interrogation of Hanna Reitsch, undated (Box 44, Folder 15)
  - Germany - School essays, 1943 (Box 44, Folder 16)
  - Germany - Regulation and orders, map, undated (Box 44, Folder 17)
  - Great Britain, 1939-1940 October (Box 44, Folder 18-21)
  - Great Britain, 1940 November - 1946 (Box 45, Folder 22-29)
  - Great Britain - Air raid damage: correspondence and photographs, 1940 (Box 45, Folder 30)
  - India, 1943 (Box 45, Folder 31)
  - Japan - Blueprint and timecard from aircraft factory, undated (Box 45, Folder 32)
  - Japan - Garrison book, [1943] (Box 45, Folder 33)
  - Netherlands, 1945 (Box 45, Folder 34)
  - Norway, 1940-1941 (Box 45, Folder 35)
  - Philippine Islands, 1941, 1945 (Box 45, Folder 36)
  - Russia, 1943-1944 (Box 45, Folder 37)
  - Sweden, 1940 (Box 45, Folder 38)
  - Switzerland, 1941 (Box 45, Folder 39)
  - United States
    - Descriptions of "Athenia" sinking, 1939 (Box 45, Folder 40)
    - Descriptions of "Athenia" sinking, 1939 (Box 46, Folder 41)
    - Descriptions of experiences on ships "San Demetrio," "Washington," "Western Prince", 1940-1941 (Box 46, Folder 42)
    - German prisoners' letters, 1943 (Box 46, Folder 43)
      General
      The material in this folder was discovered to be missing in April 2017.
  - United States - Hawaii
    - Description of Pearl Harbor attack, 1941 December 9 (Box 46, Folder 44)
    - Diaries, 1942-1943 (Box 46, Folder 45)
  - Uruguay, 1940 (Box 46, Folder 46)
    The contents of this folder were discovered to be missing in April 2017.
  - Memorabilia
    - Miscellaneous (Box 47, Folder 47)
    - Re: Iran from U.S. Minister Louis G. Dreyfus (Box 47, Folder 48)
    - notebooks - "Wasserbuch der Filterkolonne", 1942 November 18- 1943 May 3 (Box 47, Folder 49)
    - Order to report for military service, issued at Munich, 1942 May 4 (Box 47, Folder 50)
    - Three printed forms of the military government during the Allied Occupation of Germany, 1945-1946 (Box 47, Folder 50)
    - Papers of the 207A Divisione Costiera. Stato Maggiore. News bulletins and troop movements, 1942 November 25- 1943 June 10 (Box 47, Folder 51)
    - Invasion scrip for France, 1944 (Box 47, Folder 51)
    - Bouquet and ribbon presented to liberating American soldiers entering Belgium, 1945 (Box 47, Folder 52)
    - Metal pins issued 1933, 1939-1940. Trier (Box 47, Folder 52)
    - United States. War ration books, Circa 1942-1944 (Box 47, Folder 52)
    - Associated Press flashes on the outbreak of the war, 1941 December 7-11 (Box 47, Folder 53)
    - Manzanar Relocation Area: scrip, 1942 (Box 47, Folder 54)
    - Photograph of first American air fighter group to work on a British carrier. Black and white. Two copies, 22x17 cm. 25x21 cm., 1943 (Box 47, Folder 55)
    - TLS from Kenneth Clark to Melville Millar, pertaining to the bombing of Pisa, Italy (Accession 95-M-187), 1971 January 28 (Box 47, Folder 56)
    - "These Are Our Men": war bond portfolio promoting a series of radio programs dedicated to the sale of war bonds (Accession 96-M-14), [1944] (Box 47, Folder 57)
    - Canadian ration books (2) in holder, [1940s] (Box 47, Folder 58)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Bound volumes of wartime front page headlines of American newspapers [photocopies] (Box 48)
  - Russian-European campaign (Box 48)
    - German language leaflets 14A-14D (Box 49)
  - Posters
    - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Agency (UNRRA); the effort on the homefront, such as buying war bonds, recruitment of nurses, and related topics (Box 50)
    - "Aufruf an die französiche Bevölkerung/Proclamation Ã la Population Française (Accession 89-M-075) (Box 50)
    - "The U.S. Navy Presents 'Hit The Beach! Demonstrating Amphibious Warfare'" [poster of a traveling exhibit, the LST-512 assault ship] (Accession 2000-M-065), 1946 (Box 50)
      See also: Accession 2000-M-076
- Additional Material, 1930s-1943; Accession 1989-M-075; 0.25; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Addition Inventory by Carol King 1989 Mar
  Received from: Donald Gallup, 1989 Mar 16
  - "A Pocket Guide to France," a publication by the War and Navy Departments geared to the American soldier, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "French Phrase Book, Technical Manual" published by the War Department, 1943 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Speed the Second Front, "by Harry Pollitt, published by the Communist Party of Great Britain, 1942 July (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - A series of German picture booklets (measuring 1 1/2" x 1 3/4" each) pertaining to Hitler: (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Der Führer und die Bewegung, 1932-1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Der Führer macht Geschichte, 1934, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Der Führer und das Winterhilfswerk, 1933-1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Des Führers Kampf in Holland (2), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Des Führers Kampf in Norwegen (2), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Des Führers Kampf zur See, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Des Führers Kampf im Osten (Books 1-2, 4-5) (2 copies of #4), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Der Führer und Sein Volk, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Poster entitled "Aufruf an die französische Bevölkerung/Proclamation À la Population Française, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Additional Material, 1940; Accession 1990-M-044; 1
  Addition inventory by Carol King 1990 Apr
  Received from: Mary A. Curry, 1990 Feb 14
  - Address by Winston Churchill, (poster), 1940 June 4 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1944, 1991-1994 (inclusive), 1994 (bulk); Accession 1996-M-070
  - Fiftieth anniversary of D-Day landings in Normandy
    - American publications [brochures, programs], 1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - English publications [brochures, programs; includes listings of exhibits at the Imperial War Museum in London depicting war in the twentieth century], 1991, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - The Stars and Stripes [daily newspaper of U.S. Armed Forces in the European Theater of Operations], 1944 June 24, July 4 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Commemorative Edition, 1994 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - "1994: Road to Victory" [fourth issue of U.S. postage stamps in the fiftieth anniversary series; first day cover] (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Once Upon a Time..." [booklet published by the Historical Society of Neuilly-la-forêt; dedicated to the 474th Fighter Group of American pilots], [1994] (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Additional Material, 1945; Accession 1997-M-068
  - "The Personal Experiences of Robert T. Booth Who Was a Prisoner of War in Belgium and Germany, January-May 1945," by Robert T. Booth (Class of 1945, ROTC), 2005 April (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The original memoir was written in 1996. The donor sent a revised 2005 version and requested that it replace the original memoir which was returned to him.
- Additional Material, Accession 1998-M-115
  - Photographs [camp life on Buota Island, Tarawa Atoll, and the Gilbert Islands (Kiribati)]; taken by camp photographer of the U. S. Navy CB Maintenance Unit 577
    - Bob Hope show, 1944 July (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "Shoot the Works" [army show], 1944 September (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Jack Benny show, 1944 October (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Air base [Buota], 1944 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-039
  - Mount Vernon Peace Council
    - Information sheets [editor, Raymond Smith Jewett (Class of 1897, Yale Sheffield Scientific School]
      - 1937-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - 1940-1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 1999-M-083
  Also includes Accession 1999-M-101
  - "Memoirs of Yale and World War II," by William Evans Scott, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and memoranda pertaining to the intelligence work of Colonels DeForest Van Slyck and William Chanler relating to American post hostilities policy towards Japan, 1945, 1960, 1970, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence of Dick Hechinger [written to family while stationed in Europe as part of 331st Infantry Regiment, 83rd Division, Army], 1944 July-1945 February (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Postcards [scenes of military life and weaponry], 1942, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Additional Material, Accession 2000-M-076
  Also includes Accession 2002-M-022
  - "History of the USS LST 512: United States Navy Traveling, Exhibit Ship,", 1945 March - 1946 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
    See also: Oversize materials for accompanying poster.
  - "The Seventy-First Came to Gunskirchen Lager" [booklet compiled by the Seventy-First Division of the U.S. Army], ca. 1945; news clipping, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Additional Material, Accession 2002-M-033
  - Persian/English, English/Persian dictionary [compiled by Ahmad Saidi, U.S. Office of War Information, for American military personnel], 1945 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Persian Voice of America [12" records recorded by Ahmad Saidi]. The following recordings have been transferred to Historical Sound Recordings, Music Library, Sterling Memorial Library; appointment with curator required.
    - Opening speech of an Iranian living in the United States (#1A, parts 1, 2) (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Prospect of World Youth (#3, part 1) (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Roosevelt's Students' Speech (#5, part 1) (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Post War Society (parts 1, 2) (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Prospect of World Youth (part 2) (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- Additional Material, 1940-1946; Accession 2005-M-010
  The accession is divided into two parts: Rationing in World War II and Photographs of naval and aerial operations in World War II. Rationing in World War II consists primarily of ration tickets, tokens, and books. Photographs of naval and aerial operations in World War II also contain a small amount of printed matter, which is mainly to help identify ships and planes.
  - Rationing in World War II
    - Alcohol and tobacco rationing, 1943 May 25, 1944 September 22, circa 1945 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Certificate of Registrar [2 with war rations books], 1942 May 4, 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Food rationing, Circa 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Gasoline rationing, Circa 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
    - Ration tokens, Circa 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - "Rationing in World War II [publication put out by the United States Office of Price Administration], 1946 November (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Tire rationing, Circa 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Various rations [including bicycles, typewriters, shoes, and others], Circa 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - War rations books two, three, and four, Circa 1942-1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs of naval and aerial operations in World War II [arranged alphabetically by location]
    - Coral Sea, 1942 June 12, 20 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Guam and Guadalcanal, 1942 November 21, December 21, 1944 July 12 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Hong Kong and Jaluit, 1944 January 16, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Kavieng [Papua New Guinea], 1943 December 25 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Komandorski Islands, 1943 June 4, August 15 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Kwajalein, Midway, and Nantucket, 1942 January 4, 1944 January 12, October 23 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Naura raid, 1943 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - New Ireland [Papua New Guinea], Undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Normandy and North Africa, 1942 Nov, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Pagan, Palau, and the Philippines, 1944 March 29,30, June 23, November 4 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Rabaul and Rekata Bay, 1942 October 25, 1943 November 5 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Saipan and Santa Cruz, 1942 October 26, 1944 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Sicily, invasion of, 1943 July-August (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Tanamboga and Gavatu Islands, 1942 August 7 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Tarawa Atoll, 1943 November 18-20 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Tonolei Harbor, 1942 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Tulagi Harbor, 1942 August 7, 9 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Vanakanau, 1943 October 12, November 10 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Location unknown
      - Allied Fleet unites and groups, Undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - British ships, Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Italian ships, Undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Japanese ship identification cards [used by Allied war planes to identify Japanese ships], 1943 June (Box 2, Folder 33-34)
      - Japanese war planes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Magazine clippings, Undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Ship models, Undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Ship/plane identification cards, Undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - "Ship Recognition Cards for Air Use" [for use by British], 1940 July-1941 November (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Ship recognition manual [for use by Japanese], Undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - United States ships, Undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 2, Folder 42-44)
    - Oversize photographs (Box 3)
- Additional Material, 2008; Accession 2010-M-123
  - "Flight Surgeon: Memories of the Military Career of David Wyatt Aiken, Sr., M.D.", 2008 (Box 1)